and remarkably little has been done about it. If you're a wizard, and you think that clean, abundant, carbon-free nuclear power is key to fighting climate change, then you have to worry that the public willingness to build nukes is going down. If you're a prophet, and you think that the solution to the same problem is these neighborhood-run solar facilities shuttling power back and forth, you have to worry that no nation anywhere in the world has devoted anything like the resources necessary to develop this technology and deploy it in the time that we need it. And if you're on either side, wizard or prophet, you have to worry that, despite the massive alarm about climate change, the amount of energy generated every year from fossil fuels has gone up by about 30 percent since the beginning of this century. So, still think we're different than the protozoa? Still think we're special? Actually, it's even worse than that. (Laughter) We're not in the streets. No seriously, if there's a difference between us and the protozoa, a difference that matters, it's not just our art and science and technology and so forth -- it's that we can yell and scream, we can go out into the streets, and, over time, change the way society works, but we're not doing it. Wizards have been arguing literally for decades that nuclear power is key to resolving climate change. But the first pro-nuke march in history occurred less than two years ago, and it was dwarfed by the anti-nuke marches of the past. Prophets have been arguing, again literally for decades, that conservation is key to keeping freshwater supplies without destroying the ecosystems that generate those freshwater supplies. But in the history of humankind, there has never been a street full of angry protesters waving signs about leaky pipes. In fact, most of the political activity in this sphere has been wizards and prophets fighting each other, protesting each other rather than recognizing that they are, fundamentally, on the same side. After all, these people are concerned about the same thing: How are we going to make our way in the world of 10 billion? The first step towards generating that necessary social movement, creating that critical mass and getting that yelling and screaming going seems obvious: wizards and prophets join together. But how are you going to do this, given the decades of hostility? One way might be this: Each side agrees to accept the fundamental premises of the other. Accept that nuclear power is safe and carbon-free, and that uranium mines can be hideously dirty and that putting large volumes of toxic waste on rickety trains and shuttling them around the countryside is a terrible idea. To me, this leads rather quickly to a vision of small, neighborhood scale, temporary nukes, nuclear power as a bridge technology while we develop and deploy renewables. Or accept that genetically modified crops are safe and that industrial agriculture has caused huge environmental problems. To me, this leads rather quickly to a vision of plant scientists devoting much more of their attention to tree and tuber crops, which can be much more productive than cereals, use much less water than cereals, and cause much less erosion than cereals. These are just ideas from a random journalist. I'm sure there's a hundred better ones right here in this room. The main point is, wizards and prophets working together have many paths to success. And success would mean much more than mere survival, important though that is. I mean, if humankind somehow survives its own outbreak, if we get food to everybody, get water to everybody, get power to everybody, if we avoid the worst effects of climate change, if we somehow safeguard the biome, it would be amazing. It would say, I think, even to a hardened cynic like me, maybe we really are special. Thank you. (Applause)
y se ha hecho muy poco para solucionarlo. Si fueran magos y pensaran que la energía nuclear limpia, abundante y libre de carbón es la clave para luchar contra el cambio climático, tienen que preocuparse de que el apoyo de la gente a construir armas nucleares disminuya. Si son profetas y piensan que la solución al mismo problema son esas instalaciones solares de barrio que llevan energía de un lado a otro, tendrán que preocuparse de que ninguna nación en el mundo dedique ningún recurso al desarrollo de esa tecnología ni la use cuando la necesitamos. Y si están en cualquiera de los bandos, magos o profetas, deben preocuparse de que, a pesar de la gran alarma sobre el cambio climático, la cantidad de energía generada cada año por combustibles fósiles ha aumentado un 30 % desde el inicio de este siglo. ¿Siguen pensando que somos distintos de los protozoos? ¿Que somos especiales? En realidad, es peor incluso. (Risas) No estamos en la calle. No, en serio. Si hay una diferencia entre nosotros y los protozoos, una diferencia importante, no solo el arte, la ciencia y la tecnología y demás, es que podemos chillar y gritar, podemos salir a la calle y con el tiempo cambiar la sociedad, pero no lo hacemos. Los magos llevan décadas argumentando que la energía nuclear es clave para resolver el cambio climático. Pero la primera manifestación pronuclear sucedió hace menos de dos años, y fue eclipsada por las marchas antinucleares del pasado. Los profetas llevan diciendo, literalmente, durante décadas, que la conservación es clave para tener agua potable sin destruir los ecosistemas que generan esas fuentes de agua potable. Pero en la historia de la humanidad nunca ha habido una calle llena de manifestantes con pancartas para protestar por tuberías dañadas. De hecho, gran parte de la actividad política en esta esfera ha sido la confrontación entre magos y profetas, en vez de reconocer que están, en gran medida, del mismo lado. Después de todo, a todos les preocupa lo mismo: ¿cómo nos las vamos a arreglar en un mundo de 10 mil millones? El primer paso para generar ese movimiento social necesario, para crear esa masa crítica y hacer que empecemos a chillar y a gritar, parece obvio: los magos y los profetas deben unirse. Pero ¿cómo se puede lograr eso dadas las décadas de hostilidad? Una forma puede ser: cada parte se compromete a aceptar las premisas fundamentales del otro. Aceptar que la energía nuclear es segura y libre de carbono, que las minas de uranio pueden ser terriblemente sucias y que poner grandes cantidades de basura tóxica en trenes desvencijados y hacerlos circular por todo el país es una idea malísima. Para mí, esto lleva con bastante rapidez a una visión de pequeña escala, a nivel barrial, con armas nucleares temporales, y la energía nuclear como un puente mientras desarrollamos las renovables. O aceptar que los cultivos modificados genéticamente son seguros y que la agricultura industrial ha causado grandes problemas medioambientales. Para mí, esto lleva con bastante rapidez a una visión de botánicos que dedican mucha más atención a los cultivos arbóreos y de tubérculos, que pueden ser mucho más productivos que los cereales, consumen menos agua que los cereales y causan menos erosión. Estas son solo ideas de un periodista cualquiera. Estoy seguro de que hay muchas más y mejores en esta sala. Lo importante es que si los magos y los profetas trabajan juntos, pueden tener éxito. Y tener éxito significaría mucho más que la simple supervivencia, que no es poco. Si la humanidad de alguna forma sobrevive a su propio brote, si conseguimos comida y agua para todos, energía para todos, si evitamos los peores efectos del cambio climático, si de alguna manera podemos conservar el bioma, sería increíble. Creo que significaría, incluso para un cínico empedernido como yo, que quizás sí seamos especiales. Gracias. (Aplausos)